Yoga Institute of America Papers, M1135
Dept. of Special Collections & University Archives
Louise Evans Eastern philosophy collection [Yoga Institute, etc.]
circa 1920-1998
M1135
Dept. of Special Collections & University Archives
24.0 Linear feet 20 manuscript boxes, 1 mf
Incoming correspondence to Sri D.R. Sukul, numerous manuscripts and pamphlets relating to eastern philosophies and religions (originally part of the library of the Yoga Institute of America), and material concerning nutrition and color and their effect on the mind and body (one of Sukul's primary interests). Also represented are personal projects that Evans was involved with, including the Famine Relief Program for India in 1967, research on John Howard Payne, and the Olympic Manufacturing Co. There are also some scrapbooks relating to her husband's tenure as publisher of a Stockton, California newspaper, 1938-1940. Material from the Yoga Institute's library includes numerous East Indian book dealer catalogs and a large pamphlet collection on yoga and its practitioners. There are photographs of Sukul, a photo album of his visit to the Panama-Pacific Exposition in San Francisco in 1915, and an oil painting representing him.
Historical Note
Evans, secretary to the Yoga Institute of America while Sri Deva Ram Sukul was president, became president on Sukul's death on Nov. 12, 1965 when the headquarters was moved to her home in Santa Barbara from New York. It had been Evans' hope that the Yoga Institute library would eventually be associated with a research institution, and shortly before her death she arranged for the collection of books and papers to come to Stanford University.
Separated Materials Note
The books and serials that formed part of the collection are being cataloged individually by title. They were probably part of the Yoga Institute of America's library.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Louise Evans, 1998; Accn 2000-031.
Access to Collection
Open for research; material must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Evans, Louise R.; Religion
- Photos, postcards, letters, typescripts, manuscripts, handwritten fragments and notes, leaflets, clippings, legal documents (including Yoga Institute / Dr. Sukul trademark registration), business correspondence, scores, various publications, miscellaneous. Includes material regarding Dr. Sukul's talks, Yoga Institute events, World Religious Alliance, etc. Mostly 1920s-1940s. (Box 1)
- Publications, financial documents, correspondence, invitations, business cards, typescripts, clippings, tear sheets, color paper, miscellaneous Incl. materials regarding "World Fellowship Program," The Universal Religious Foundation," "The New School of Health," Natural Science Society, American League for India's Freedom, Applied Yoga Institute (students' lists), etc. Mostly 1930s-1950s. (Box 2)
- Clippings, a scrapbook, publications, catalogs, programs, photos, price lists, typescripts, miscellaneous 1930s-1960s. Clippings are fragile. (Box 3)
- Dr. Sukul's invoices and other papers, correspondence (marked "private"); "College of the Pacific, Art of Language" documents, mostly correspondence; NASA publications; postcards; photos; memorabilia; scores; typescripts; off prints; miscellaneous Incl. materials related to John Howard Payne. Some materials are fragile. (Box 4)
- Correspondence, agreements, negative photocopies of typewritten materials, tear sheets; investigation reports on the case of Rev. William Estep; typescripts, handwritten notes, clippings, off prints, financial documents, manuscripts, Dr. Sukul's travel records (mostly hotels' stationery), India Society materials, photos, miscellaneous Some materials are fragile. (Box 5)
- Clippings, photos, newsletters, scores, typescripts, publications, miscellaneous material. Some materials are fragile and / or damaged. (Box 6)
- Publications, clippings, tear sheets, handwritten notes, typescripts, charts, letters, cards, publicity forms, announcements, catalogs, miscellaneous materials. (Box 7)
- Catalogs, publications, correspondence, Carnegie Institution of Washington materials, typescripts, photos, clippings / photocopies of clippings, scores, flyers, handwritten notes / fragments, memorabilia ( a piece of embroidery), miscellaneous materials. (Box 8)
- Typescripts, an audiocassette, postcards, flyers, correspondence, clippings, photos, miscellaneous (Box 9)
- Postcards, leaflets, correspondence, typescripts, business cards, medical and financial info related to Ms. Evans, her diaries, newsletters, brochures, newspapers, tear sheets, photos, miscellaneous (Box 10)
- Clippings, tear sheets, publications, correspondence (some marked "private"), manuscripts, handwritten notes, typescripts, catalogs, newspapers, miscellaneous Some documents are related to The India Society. (Box 11)
- Publications, Ms. Evans's tax documents, leaflets, clippings, tear sheets, correspondence, brochures, photos, flyers; documents related to World Fellowship of Faiths, Yoga Publication Society, Applied Yoga Institute of America; reprints, miscellaneous (Box 12)
- Students' lists, address labels, handwritten notes, correspondence, announcements, bulletins, clippings, posters, financial documents, address / notebooks, photos, miscellaneous (Box 13)
- Financial documents, photo albums (incl. one titled "Panama Pacific," 1915), brochures, typescripts, Sri Deva Ram Sukul's personal file, business / legal correspondence. (Box 14)
- Typescripts, correspondence, stationery, miscellaneous handwritten notes, photos, clippings, etc. (Box 15)
- Academy of Self-Attainment (California) materials; typescripts, correspondence, clippings, students' lists, a scrapbook, miscellaneous (Box 16)
- Publications, leaflets, programs, newspapers, tear sheets, clippings, typescripts, newsletters, enrollment / membership forms, correspondence, miscellaneous (Box 17)
- Notebooks, patents' information and documents, typescripts, posters / handouts, correspondence, business cards, photos, financial documents, clippings, PR materials, newsletters, catalogs, leaflets, miscellaneous 1960s-1970s, miscellaneous dates. (Box 18)
- Catalogs, leaflets, brochures, photos, clippings, Dishan Spectro-Chrome Institute materials, newsletters, publications, correspondence, negatives, miscellaneous (Box 19)
- Newspapers, clippings, leaflets, books, brochures, miscellaneous publications, correspondence, postcards. (Box 20)
- Scrapbooks, clippings, leaflets, miscellaneous publications, correspondence. (Box 21)
- Teaching materials, The Asia Society materials, correspondence, brochures, posters, leaflets, miscellaneous publications, typescripts, clippings, Henry George School of Social Science materials, medical papers, photos, miscellaneous notes, library cards, business cards, postcards. (Box 22)
- Typescripts, correspondence, posters, catalogs, medical / financial papers, photos, Dr. Sukul's lectures, clippings, leaflets, a notebook, miscellaneous notes, etc. (Box 23)
- Typescripts, brochures, leaflets, Seymour School of Musical Re-Education materials, drafts, clippings, photos, Rhodia Chemical Company materials, correspondence, off prints of materials about John Howard Payne, newsletters, postcards, etc. (Box 24)
- Memorabilia (wooden-metal artifacts, a piece of embroidery, jewelry, miscellaneous items), photos (Box 25)
- Two scrapbooks ("Editorials" and "Letters") containing clippings, 1930s (Box 26)
- Two scrapbooks (untitled) containing letters and clippings, 1930s (Box 27)
- Letters / brochures, tear sheets, photos, typescripts, miscellaneous handwritten notes, financial documents, correspondence, postcards, The National Geographic Society materials, newsletters, clippings, Summer School (Chicago, 1928) materials, photocopies of various articles, scores, miscellaneous (Box 28)
- Correspondence, leaflets / brochures, donation forms, clippings, tear sheets, photos, posters, business cards, catalogs, typescripts, handwritten notes, miscellaneous (Box 29)
- Correspondence, typescripts, posters, announcements, photos, clippings, medical articles, scores, invitations, catalogs, leaflets / brochures, miscellaneous; Louise Evans' business license, framed, July 26, 1977. (Box 30)
- Correspondence, financial documents, photos, clippings, negatives, catalogs and publications, photocopies of clippings, leaflets / brochures, financial documents, miscellaneous handwritten notes, typescripts, etc. (Box 31)
- India Pilgrimage Trip materials (leaflets, brochures, handouts, financial documents), clippings, correspondence, typescripts, postcards, stationery, photos, students' lists, newsletters, digests, maps, miscellaneous (Box 32)
- India Pilgrimage Trip materials, continued (brochures, leaflets, maps, etc. regarding Japan, Italy, Egypt and other countries); postcards, clippings, newsletters, miscellaneous (Box 33)
- Yoga Institute Bank Records, 1972, 1974-1977; catalogs, typescripts, manuscripts and notes, instructions for students, "Cook Book" (fragments of a typescript), miscellaneous (Box 34)
- Cook Book Original (fragments of a typescript, random notes), typescripts, instructions, exercises, "The Self Improvement League" materials, photos, "The Holy Order of Krishna" materials, class enrollment cards, miscellaneous notes. Some materials are marked as "confidential". (Box 35)
- Drawings, posters, photos, postcards, publications ("Shree Sayaji Vijay Baroda H.H. Maharaja Pratapsiuh Coronation Issue"; "The New York Times Magazine," "East West Journal," "Life," "The Orient Illustrated Weekly," a catalog), 1930s-1970s, no date. Some items are fragile. (Box 36)
- Drawings, correspondence (incl. recommendation letters), clippings, photos, typescripts, handwritten fragments and notes, posters and small wall signs, Electronical Medical Foundation bulletins and other materials, The American Philosopher Society publications, miscellaneous. Some items are damaged. (Box 37)
- Magazines, newspapers, publications ("Practical Yoga," "The Divine Life," "Cosmos," "The Message," "Dharma," "Psychology," "Time," "The Times. The Indian Number," "The Nation," "Tokyo Gazette," "Sunrise," "Gesar" (Nyingma Institute), "A Voice from India," "Orient," "The Vedic Magazine," "Life and Action," "Inner Culture," "The Bande Mataram," "The Centennial Post," "The United States of India," "The American Vegetarian-Hygienist"), 1930s-1970s; typescripts, clippings, postcards, posters, miscellaneous. Some items are damaged and fragile. (Box 38)
- Flex records, a tape, two recordings (33 1/3 RPM postcards), no date (Box 39)
- Typescripts, small brochures, pamphlets, miscellaneous material. (Box 40)
- Oil painting of Sri Sukol by Luesone 1959. (Othertype 1)